>> (Phillip Roberts) hello, come in and sit
down. So for the last session before the afternoon
break, we have Phillip Roberts who works at
Andea and is here from London ‑‑ Scotland.
Edinbrough.  ‑‑ wow, ten second memory,
he's going to talk about the vent loop. If
everyone could give Phillip a big brownedder
round of applause.
>> Phillip Roberts: Okay hello everyone, thanks
for coming to the side track, it's awesome
to see it packed out in here. Can everyone
give me a stretch. I needed to stretch, so
I look less weird. I want to talk about the
event loop and what the heck is the event
loop, as in the event loop inside JavaScript.
So first up, as he said I work for AndYet
which is an awesome little Dev shop in the
US, look us up if you need help with real‑time
stuff. That's what we're good at. So, about
18 months ago--I'm a paid professional JavaScript
developer--I thought to myself how does, like
JavaScript actually work? And I wasn't entirely
sure. I'd heard V8 as a term, chrome's Runtime
didn't really know what that meant, what that
did. I'd heard things like single threaded,
you know obviously I'm using callbacks. How
do callbacks work? I started a journey of
like reading and research and experimenting
in the browser which basically started like
this.
‑‑ I was kind of like JavaScript what
are you. I'm a single threaded single concurrent
language ‑‑ right. yeah, cool, I have
a call stack, an event loop, a callback queue,
and some other APIs and stuff.  ‑‑ rite.
I did not do a computer science degree. I
mean, these words, they're words, so I heard
about V8 and the various Runtimes and different
browsers so I looked to V8 do you have a call
stack, an event loop, a callback queue, and
some other APIs and stuff, I have a call stack
and a heap, I don't know what those other
things are, okay, interesting so basically
18 months passed. And I think I get this.
(Laughing) and so, this is what I want to
share with you today. Hopefully this will
be useful if you're relatively new to JavaScript,
help you understand why JavaScript is so weird
when you compare it to other languages you
might used why callbacks are a thing, cause
us hell but are required. And if you're an
experienced JavaScript developer hopefully
give you some fresh insights how the Runtime
you're using works so you can think about
it a little better. So if we look at the JavaScript
Runtime itself like V8 which is the Runtime
inside Chrome. This is a simplified view of
what JavaScript Runtime is. The heap, where
memory allocation happens, and then there's
the call stack, which is where your stack
frames are and all that kind of stuff, but,
if you, like, clone the V8 code base and grep
for things like setTimeout or DOM or HTTP
request, they're not in there, they don't
exist in V8, which was a surprise to me. It's
first thing you use when you start thinking
about async stuff and it's not in the V8 source.
Hmm ... interesting. So, over this 18 months
of discovery I come to realize this is really,
this is really the bigger picture, this is
what I'm hoping to get you on board with today
and understand what these pieces are, we have
the V8 Runtime but then we have these things
called web APIs which are extra things that
the browser provides. DOM, AJAX, time out,
things like that, we have this mythical event
loop and the callback queue. I'm sure you've
heard some of these terms before, but maybe
you don't quite understand how these pieces
pull together. So, I'm going to start from
the beginning, some of this will be new, to
words might be new to people, other people
will get this. We're going to quickly move
on from here, bear with me if this is obvious,
I think for a lot of people it's not. So,
JavaScript is a single threaded programming
language, single threaded Runtime, it has
a single call stack. And it can do one thing
at a time, that's what a single thread means,
the program can run one piece of code at a
time. So, let's try and visualize that just
to get our heads around what that mean, so
if I have some code like this on your left,
we've got a few functions, a function multiplier
which multiplies two numbers, square which
calls multiply with the same number twice,
a function which prints the square of a number
of calling square and then calling console.log
and then at the bottom of our file we actually
run print square, this code all good? Make
sense? Cool. So, if we run this, well, I should
back up a step, so the call stack is basically ‑‑
it's a data structure which records basically
where in the program we are, if we step into
a function, we put something on to the stack,
if we return from a function, we pop off the
top of the stack that's all the stack can
do, ‑‑ so if you run this file, there's
kind of a main function, right, like the file
itself, so, we push that on to the stack.
Then we have some function definitions, they're
just like defining the state of the world,
and finally we got to print square, right,
so print square is a function call, so we
push that on to the stack, and immediately
inside print square, push on to the stack,
which calls multiply, now we have a return
statement, we multiply A and B and we return,
when we return we pop something off the stack,
so, pop, multiplier of the stack, returning
to square, return to print square, console.log,
there's no return, it's implicit, because
we got to the end of the function, and we're
done so that's like a visualization of the
call stalk, does that make sense? (Yes, Phil)
even if you haven't thought about the call
stack before, you've come across it when you've
been doing browser‑side development, so
if we have code like this, a function baz
which calls bar, which calls Foo, which throws
an error if we run it in Chrome we see this.
And it prints the stack trace, right, the
state of the stack when that error happened,
so, uncaught error oops Foo, bar, Baz, anonymous
function, which is our main. Equally, if you've
heard the term like blowing the stack, this
is an example of that. Have a function foo
which calls Foo , so what's going to happen
? We have a function main which calls foo
which calls foo, which calls foo, which calls
foo, and ultimately chrome says, you probably
didn't mean to call foo 16,000 times recursively,
I'll just kill things for you and you can
figure out where your bug lies, right. So
although I may be representing a new side
of the call stack you have some sense of it
in your development practice already. So,
the big question then comes is like what happens
when things are slow? So, we talk about blocking
and blocking behavior and blocking, there's
no strict definition of what is and didn't
blocking, really it's just code that's slow.
So console.log isn't slow, doing a while loop
from one to ten billion is slow, network requests
are slow. Image requests are slow. Things
which are slow and on that stack are what
are blocking means. So heres a little example,
so let's say we have, this is like a fake
bit of code, getSynchronous, right, like jQuery
is like, AJAX request. What would happen if
those were synchronous requests, forget what
we know about async callbacks they're synchronous.
If we go through it like we have, we call
getSync and then we wait, because then we're
doing network request, network is relative
to computers, are slow, hopefully that network
requests completes, we can move on, wait,
move on. Wait, and, I mean, this network request
might never finish, so ... yeah, I guess I'll
go home. Finally those three, you know blocking
behaviors complete and we can clear the stack,
right. So in a programming language is single
threaded you're not using threads like say
Ruby, that's what happens, right, we make
a network request, we have to just wait till
it's done, because we have no way of handling
that. Why is this actually a problem? The
problem is because we're running code in browsers.
So, let's you ‑‑ here we go, okay. So
this is just, this is Chrome, this is the
code I just ran. Browsers don't give us ‑‑
well they do give us synchronous AJAX request,
I'm faking this out with a big while loop,
because it's synchronous, I basically while
loop for five seconds before continuing, so
if I open up the console here. We can see
what happens, so with request foo.com, why
this is happening, I can't do anything, right,
even the run button hasn't finished rerendering
the fact that I clicked it. The browser is
blocked, it's stuck, it can't do anything
until those requests complete. And then all
hell breaks loose because I did some stuff,it
figured that out I'd done it, it couldn't
actually render it. Couldn't do anything.
That's because if that call stack has things
on it, and here it's got these yeah, it's
still going. We've got the synchronous request,
the browser can't do anything else. It can't
render, it can't run any other code, it's
stuck. Not ideal, right if we want people
to have nice fluid UIs, we can't block the
stack. So, how do we handle this? Well the
simplest solution we're provided with is asynchronous
callbacks, there's almost no blocking functions
in the browser, equally in node, they're all
made asynchronous, which basically means we
run some code, give it a callback, and run
that later, if you've seen JavaScript you've
seen asynchronous callbacks, what does this
actually look like. Simple example to remind
people where we're at. Code like this, console.log
hi. Write, we run the setTimeout, but that
queue's the console log for future so we skip
on to JSConf and then five seconds later we
log "there" right, make sense? Happy. Basically
that's setTimeout is doing something. So,
asynchronous callbacks with regards to the
stacks we saw before ... how does this work?
Let's run the code. Console.log hi. setTimeout.
We know it doesn't run immediately, we know
it's going to run in five seconds time, we
can't push it on to the stack, somehow it
just disappears, we don't have like a way
of describing this yet, but we'll come to
it. We log JSConfEU, clear, five seconds later
somehow magically "there" appears on the stack.
How does that happen? And that's ‑‑ this
is basically where the event loop comes in
on concurrency. Right, so I've been kind of
partially lying do you and telling you that
JavaScript can only do one thing at one time.
That's true the JavaScript Runtime can only
do one thing at one time. It can't make an
AJAX request while you're doing other code.
It can't do a setTimeout while you're doing
another code. The reason we can do things
concurrently is that the browser is more than
just the Runtime. So, remember this diagram,
the JavaScript Runtime can do one thing at
a time, but the browser gives us these other
things, gives us these we shall APIs, these
are effectively threads, you can just make
calls to, and those pieces of the browser
are aware of this concurrency kicks in. If
you're back end person this diagram looks
basically identical for node, instead of web
APIs we have C++ APIs and the threading is
being hidden from you by C++. Now we have
this picture let's see how this code runs
in a more full picture of what a browser looks
like. So, same as before, run code, console
log hi, logs hi to the console, simple. now
we can see what happens when we call setTimeout.
We are ‑‑ we pass this callback function
and a delay to the setTimeout call. Now setTimeout
is an API provided to us by the browser, it
doesn't live in the V8 source, it's extra
stuff we
get in that we're running the JavaScript run
time in. The browser kicks off a timer for
you. And now it's going to handle the count
down for you, right, so that means our setTimeout
call, itself is now complete, so we can pop
off the stack. “JSConfEU”, clear, so,
now we've got this timer in the web API, which
five seconds later is going to complete. Now
the web API can't just start modifying your
code, it can't chuck stuff onto the stack
when it's ready if it did it would appear
randomly in the middle of your code so this
is where the task queue or callback queue
kicks in. Any of the web APIs pushes the callback
on to the task queue when it's done. Finally
we get to the event loop, title of the talk,
what the heck is the event loop is like the
simplest little piece in this whole equation,
and it has one very simple job.
The event loops job is to look at the stack
and look at the task queue. If the stack is
empty it takes the first thing on the queue
and pushes it on to the stack which effectively
run it. So here we can see that now the stack
is clear, there's a callback on the task queue,
the event loop runs, it says, oh, I get to
do something, pushes the callback on to the
stack. Remember it's the stack is like JavaScript
land, back inside V8, the callback appears
on the stack, run, console.log “there”,
and we're done. Does that make sense? Everyone
where me? Awesome! Okay. So, now we can see
how this works with probably one of the first
encounters you would have had with Async stuff
which for some weird reason someone says says
you have to call setTimeout zero, ‑‑
okay, you want me to run the function in zero
time? Why would I wrap it in a setTimeout?
Like the first time you run across this, if
you're like me,i see it doing something, but
I don't know why. The reason is, generally,
if you're trying to defer something until
the stack is clear. So we know looking at
this, if you've written JavaScript, that we're
going to see the same result, we're going
to see “hi” “JSConf”, and “there”
is going to appear at the end. We can see
how that happens. The setTimeout zero, now
it's going to complete immediately and push
it on to the queue, remember what I said about
the event loop, it has to wait till the stack
is clear before it can push the callback on
to the stack, so your stack is going to continue
to run, console.log “hi”, “JSConfEU”
and clear, now the event loop can kick in
and call your callback. That's like an example
of setTimeout zero, is deferring that execution
of code, for whatever reason to the end of
the stack. Or until stack is clear. Okay.
So, all these web APIs work the same way,
if we have AJAX request, we make an AJAX request
to the URL with a callback, works the same
way, oops sorry, console log, “hi”, make
an AJAX request, the code for running that
AJAX request does not live in JavaScript Runtime
but in the browser as a web API, so we spin
it up with a callback in the URL, your code
can continue to run. Until that XHR request
completes, or it may never complete, it's
okay, the stack can continue to run, assuming
it completes, gets pushed to the queue,picked
up by the event loop and it's run. That's
all that happens when an Async call happens.
Let's do a crazy complicated example, I hope
this going to work, if you haven't realized
all this is in keynote there's like I don't
know 500 animation steps in this whole deck.
(code blows up, flames animation) (Applause)
J Whew ... no ... so ... interesting, we're
given a link. Hmm ... is this big enough,
can people see? Okay, so basically I wrote
this talk for Scotland JS, after the talk
I broke half of the slides and could not be
bothered to redo all the slides because it
was a total pain in the ass in keynote to
do it so I took much easier route (Laughing)
of writing a tool that can visualize the JavaScript
Runtime at Runtime, and it's called loop.
So, let's just run this example and, which
was kind of the example that we had on the
previous slide, I haven't shimmed XHR yet,
it's doable I just haven't done it. As you
can see the code, we're going to log something,
this is a shim around addEventListener, setTimeout
and we're going to do a console.log. ‑‑
I'm going to run it and see what happens so
... add a DOM API, add a timeout, code is
going to continue to run, pushes the callback
into the queue which runs, and we're done.
If I click on here then it's going to ... trigger
the web API, queue the callback for the click
and run it. if I cluck a hundred times we
can see what happens. I clicked, the click
doesn't get processed immediately, itself
gets pushed to the queue, as the queue gets
processed, eventually my click is going to
get dealt with, right. So I have a few more
examples I'm going to run through here. Here
we go, okay, so, I'm just going to run through
a few examples just to kind of talk about
a few things that you might have run in to
and not thought about with Async APIs, In
this example we call setTimeout four times
with the one second delay, and console.log
“hi”. By the time the callbacks get queued...
that fourth callback we asked for a one second
delay, and it's still waiting, the callback
hasn't run, right .
this illustrates the ‑‑ like what time
out is actually doing, it's not a guaranteed
time to execution, it's a minimum time to
execution, just like setTimeout zero doesn't
run the code immediately it runs the code
next‑ish, sometime, right? So ... in this
example I want to talk about callbacks, so,
depending on who, speak to and how they phrase
things, callbacks can be one of two things,
callbacks can be any function that another
function calls or callbacks can be more explicitly
an asynchronous callback as in one that will
get pushed back on the callback queue in the
future. This bit of code illustrates the difference,
right. The forEach method on an array, it
doesn't run, it takes a function, which you
could call a callback, but it's not running
it asynchronously, it's running it within
the current stack. We could define an asynchronous
forEach so it can take an array, a callback
and for each item in the array it's going
to do a setTimeout zero with that callback,
I guess this should pass in the value, but
any way, so, I'm going to run it and we can
see what the difference is, so for the first
block of code that runs, it's going to sit
and block the stack, right? Until it's complete,
whereas in the Async version, okay, it's slowed
down, but we're basically going to queue a
bunch of callbacks and they're going to clear
and then we can actually run through and do
a console.log. In this example the console.log
is fast, so the benefit of doing it asynchronously
is not obviously but let's say you're doing
some slow processing on each element in the
array. I think I have that shown somewhere
no, no, I don't. Okay. So let's say ‑‑
Ooops. So I have a delay function which is
just slow, it's just a slow thing. So ... let's
say processing Async and here processing Sync.
Okay, now, I'm going to turn on a thing I've
literally hacked together this morning, which
is to simulate the repaint or the render in
the browser, something I haven't touched on
is how all of this interacts with rendering ‑‑
I've kind of touched on it but not really
explained it. So, basically the browser is
kind of constrained by what you're doing javaScript,
the browser would like to repaint the screen
every 16.6 milliseconds, 60 frame a second
is ideal, that's the fastest it will do repaints
if it can. But it's constrained by what you're
doing in JavaScript for various reasons, so
it can't actually do a render if there is
code on the stack, right. Like the render
kind of call is almost like a callback in
itself. It has to wait till the stack is clear.
The difference is that the render is given
a higher priority than your callback, every
16 milliseconds it's going to queue a rend,
wait till the stack is clear before it can
actually do that render. So this is ‑‑
this render queue is just simulating a render,
every second it's can I do a render? Yes,
can I do a render? Yes. Where, because our
code isn't doing anything now. If I run the
code, you can see while we're doing this slow
synchronous loop through the array, our render
is blocked, right, if our render is blocked
you can't select text on the screen, you can't
click things and see the response, right,
like the example I showed earlier. In this
example, okay, it's blocked while we queue
up the async time out, that relatively quick
but we're given ‑‑ we're kind of giving
the render a chance between each element because
we've queued it up asynchronously to jump
in there and do the render, does that make
sense?
>> Yeah
>> Yeah, cool. So, that's just kind of ‑‑
this is just like a simulation of how the
rendering works, but it just really shows
you when people say don't block the event
loop, this is exactly what they're talking
about. They're saying don't put shitty slow
code on the stack because when you do that
the browser can't do what it needs to do,
create a nice fluid UI. This is why when you're
doing things like image processing or Animating
too many things gets sluggish if you're not
careful about how you queue up that code.
So an example of that, we can see with the
scroll handlers ‑‑ so scroll handle ‑‑
like scroll events in the DOM trigger a lot,
right, they trigger like ‑‑ I presume
they trigger on every frame like every 16
milliseconds, if I have code like this this
right. On document.scroll, animate something,
or do some work. If I have this code, like
as I scroll it's going to queue up like a
ton of callbacks right. And then it has to
go through and process all of those and each
of the processing of those is slow, then,
okay, you're not blocking the stack, you're
flooding the queue with queued events. So,
this is like just helping visualize, I guess,
what happens when you actually trigger all
these callbacks, there's way you can debounce
that to basically say okay, we're going to
queue up all those events, but let's do the
slow work every few seconds or until the user
stops scrolling for some amount of time I
think that's basically it. There's a whole
other talk in how the hell this works. Because
basically in running the code, like this code
runs at Runtime, right, and it's slowed down
by I run it through a Esprima a JavaScript
parser, I insert a big while loop, that takes
half a second, it just slow motions the code.
Ship it to web worker and do a whole bunch
of stuff to visualize what's happening while
doing it at run time that makes sense. A whole
other talk in that. I'm super excited about
it and will talk to anyone about it after
because I think it's kind of neat, so with
that, thanks very much ( applause)